它所做的是通过获取第二个参数并将其传入来取消嵌套。
What it's done is unnested it by taking a second argument and passing it in.
如果这里的第二个参数又高了，对，但是
And if the second argument here is just high again, right, but
这是原来的高，这有点奇怪，对吧？
it's the original high, which is kind of weird, right?
我们给它这个 x，这个 x 处理它并传入转换后的 x。
We gave it this x, and this one processed it and passed in the transformed x.
这个在外面运行原始的x。
This one's running the original x on the outside.
所以我们得到了像 x hat 之类的东西。
So we get this kind of like x hat or something.
就像原来的x。
It's like the original x.
那么我们会得到小写字母的惊叹号吗？
So the exclaim that we would get the lowercase one right?
这样做，因为它是 x 帽子，当然。
Do that up cuz it's x hat, of course.
[笑]让我们回到x。
[LAUGH] let's just go back to x.
所以我们得到了原始的 x。
So we get the original x.
让我们把它放在一个有上一个和那个的数组中，所以
Let's put this in an array that has the upper one and that one, so
我们可以同时看到两者。
we can see both at the same time.
让我把两个都拿来。
Let me get both here.
所以这种行为在前期看起来不是很有用，但它会让我们
So this behavior doesn't seem very useful upfront, but it will allows us
要做的是通过我们的整个程序线程类隐形环境。
to do is thread kind of invisible environment through our whole program.
这就是我们称这个读者的原因，因为 x 没有被转换。
That's why we call this reader, is because x wasn't transformed.
x 只是有点通过，我可以随时访问它。
x is just kinda carried through and I can just gain access to it whenever I want.
所以当我开始转换时，我的输入仍然可以恢复到这种原始状态。
So as I start transforming, my input can still get back to this kind of original.
另一个有趣的事情是我们可以创建一个函数，取 x，然后
Something else that's interesting is we can make a function of, takes x, and
我们将只返回一个接受任何内容的函数，并将 x 放在那里。
we'll just return a function that takes whatever, and just puts the x in there.
所以我们可以从一个Hello函数开始。
So we can start with a function of Hello.
然后我们可以映射到上层。
And then we can map to upper on that.
让我们这样做，这样我们就能得到一些空间。
Let's do this so we can get some room.
现在发生了什么？
What's happening now?
这有点奇怪，对吧？
This is kind of weird, right?
这将是你好或你好。
It's going to be hi or hello.
我们现在有两个参数，我们得到了 Hello 和 hi&#39;，那么这里发生了什么？
We have two arguments now, we got Hello and hi', so what's happening here?
我们从一个函数开始，这里的参数是 x 作为它的结果，
We're starting with a function with the argument here x as its result,
我们将映射过去。
and we're gonna map over that.
我们可以整天映射它。
We can map over it all day long.
我们可以忽略这个嗨的东西，对，这只是大写的tillow。
We can ignore this hi thing, right, this will just be uppercase tillow.
但是如果我们想访问第二个参数，
But if we want to access the second argument,
让我们让它更正式一点。
let's make it a little bit more formal.
假设这是端口 3000，对吗？
Let's say this is the port 3000, right?
如果我想访问我的配置，
If I wanna access my config,
突然之间，我可以在我的函数中创建一个函数。
all of a sudden I can make a function here inside my function.
这给了我配置。
And that gives me the config.
所以让我们展示一下，我们同时拥有了我们的鞋面和我们的配置。
So let's just show, we've got our upper and our config at the same time.
太好了，我们正在凭空捏造东西，然后
Sweet, we're pulling stuff out of thin air, and
通常你会看到这样的框架，
typically you'll see this kind of framed this way,
我们有一个函数运行。
where we have a function running through.
然后在这个应用程序中间的某个地方，我只想获取我的配置和
And then somewhere in the middle of this this app, I just wanna grab my config and
它无处不在。
there it comes out of nowhere.
我不知道它是如何工作的，这太神奇了。
I don't know how that works, it's amazing.
所以让我们再做一个函数，让它更方便一点。
So let's make one more function to make this a little bit more convenient.
我们会说 Fn.ask。
And we'll say Fn.ask.
而 Fn.ask 已经是一个函数，它说，
And Fn.ask is just already a function that says,
好吧，我会把我手里的东西都给你。
okay, I'm going to just give you whatever I'm holding.
就像配置到配置一样，对吧？
Just like config to config, right?
所以这是一个方便的函数，而不是这个奇怪的函数
So this is a convenience function that says instead of this bizarre function
在我的东西中间的构造函数，我可以说，
constructor in the middle of my stuff, I'm able to say,
问，然后我把我的配置拿出来。
ask, and then I get my config out.
我可以同时在配置中返回上层。
And I can return upper in config at the same time.
请注意我们正在执行链，对，因为 ask 是另一个函数。
And notice we're doing chain, right, because ask is another function.
然后我们可以用 config 运行它，然后我们就炸了，明白吗？
And then we can run it with config and and we blow up, see?
完毕。
Done.
[笑] 不，这里发生了什么？
[LAUGH] No, what's happening here?
ask 没有定义，它是 Fn.ask。
ask is not defined, it's Fn.ask.
我们去那里，我们去。
There we go and there we go.
这是读者单子。
This is the reader monad.
它在功能架构中非常有用。
It's insanely helpful during function architecture.
最近，图书馆开始更多地研究 Zio 或 Rio 的签名。
Lately, libraries have started to work way more on this signature of Zio or Rio.
这个想法是你可以在这里进行依赖注入。
The idea is that you can do dependency injection in here.
我不仅可以拥有我的配置，还可以拥有
I could have not just my configuration but
我所有的依赖项，比如我的数据库连接。
all of my dependencies like my db connection.
无论我想在本地存储中使用什么策略
And whatever my strategy for whatever I wanna use in my local storage or
无论如何，然后我就可以摆脱我的环境了。
whatever, and then I can just get my environment out.
现在我有了我所有的效果。
And now I have all my my effects.
我只是不知从哪里通过了那些。
I've just kind of passed in those out of nowhere.
所以这是我们可以使用的非常有用的技术，但那是读者。
So this is a really useful technique that we can use, but that's reader.
超酷。
Super cool.
我不打算谈论状态，但状态正是这样。
I'm not gonna talk about state, but state is exactly this.
这就像完全一样的东西，除了我们能够通过一个状态并
It's like the same exact thing, except we're able to thread a state through and
修改它。
modify it.
而这个不允许你修改它。
And this one doesn't let you modify it.
我只是觉得它在 JavaScript 中不像其他人那样有用。
I just don't find it as useful maybe in JavaScript as others do.
但我们可以稍后再谈。
But we can talk about that later.